Juliana L. Knoepfmacher Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Juliana L. Knoepfmacher Papers 1929-1980 (bulk 1940-1960)
MSS60343
Knoepfmacher, Juliana L., 1899-1974
500 items
6 containers
2.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Psychoanalyst, social worker, and educator. Case files, lectures, speeches, writings, notes, minutes, agenda, correspondence, memoranda, biographical material, and printed matter documenting Knoepfmacher’s work as a child therapist and her writings on the treatment of children.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Knoepfmacher, Juliana L., 1899-1974.
Organizations
Jewish Board of Guardians.; Paul Federn Study Group.
Subjects
Child analysis.; Child psychology.; Montessori method of education--Austria--Vienna.; Psychoanalysis--United States--Societies, etc.; Psychoanalysis.; Social work with children--United States.
Occupations
Educators.; Psychoanalysts.; Social workers.
Provenance
The papers of Juliana L. Knoepfmacher, psychoanalyst, social worker, and educator, were a gift from the estate of Hugo and Juliana L. Knoepfmacher via the Sigmund Freud Archives in 1982.
Access and Restrictions
Restrictions apply governing the use, photoduplication, or publication of items in this collection. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division for information concerning these restrictions. In addition, many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1899 Born, Vienna, Austria
1918 1921 Led homeless children's transport from Vienna, Austria, to the Netherlands for the Red Cross
1927 M.A., Teacher's College, Vienna, Austria
1927 1935 Training for applied psychoanalysis for teachers and social workers, Psychoanalytic Institute, Vienna, Austria Underwent psychoanalysis with Richard Sterba Married Hugo Knoepfmacher (died 1980) Director of a Montessori school, Vienna, Austria
1941 Emigrated to the United States M.S.S., Smith College School of Social Work, Northampton, Mass.
1941 1954 Senior training supervisor, Jewish Board of Guardians
1942 Published “The Use of Play in Diagnosis and Therapy in Psychiatric Case Work,” Smith College Studies in Social Work (March): 217-262
1945 1949 Consultant, Jewish Child Guidance Bureau, Newark, N.J.
1946 Published “Child Guidance Work Based on Psychoanalytic Concepts,” The Nervous Child (April): 178-198
1949 Published “The Length of Treatment in a Child Guidance Clinic,” Jewish Social Service Quarterly (December): 208-228
1950 1960 Faculty member, Postgraduate Center for Mental Health, Jewish Child Guidance Bureau, Newark, N.J.
1951 1953 Directed workshop on treatment of schizophrenic children
1953 1957 Participant, Borderline Project under Hyman Spotnitz
1954 Joined Peter Glauber in his private practice in New York, N.Y.
1955 1974 In private practice
1959 1962 Faculty member, National Psychological Association for Psychoanalysis
1963 Faculty member, Boston University School of Social Work, Boston, Mass.
1974 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Juliana Knoepfmacher (1899-1974), known primarily as “Lia” during the American period of her career after the 1940s, span the years 1929-1980, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the years 1940-1960. The collection consists of professional files relating to her work as a child therapist and her writings on the treatment of children. The papers contain lectures, speeches, writings, notes, minutes, agenda, correspondence, memoranda, biographical material, and printed matter arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material. Patient case files and notes are closed.
Much of the collection relates to Knoepfmacher’s professional associations and her work as a training supervisor with the Jewish Board of Guardians in New York City. Minutes, memoranda, and reports from the Jewish Board of Guardians and other organizations explore such topics as supervision and teaching methods, time in treatment, treatment goals, diagnostic criteria, private practice, and fee structures. Files from the Paul Federn Study Group feature meeting notes and discussion material, including a paper by August Aichhorn on transference in child guidance dated 1936. Writings by Knoepfmacher include her account of a Montessori school she directed in Vienna from 1927 to 1937 and articles and papers principally relating to her work in the field of child therapy. The balance of the professional files include speeches, lectures, and writings of others.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
Container List
- Biographical file, 1980, undated (Box 1)
- Boston University School of Social Work, Boston, Mass., 1961 (Box 1)
- Cases See Closed (Box 1)
- Certificates, 1959-1969 (Box 1)
- Child Welfare League of America, Central Regional Conference program, 1968 (Box 1)
- German material (Box 1)
- Group therapy, 1949 See Closed (Box 1)
- Jewish Board of Guardians, Time and Treatment Project, 1949-1950 See also Closed (Box 1)
- Letters to Knoepfmacher, 1945-1960, undated See also Closed (Box 1)
- Memoranda, 1949-1959 (Box 1)
- Minutes, 1941-1950 (Box 1)
- Miscellany (Box 1)
- Montessori school, Vienna, Austria (Box 1)
- National Association of Social Workers, Private Practice Committee report, 1955 (Box 1)
- Paul Federn Study Group, 1936-1960, undated (Box 1)
- Printed matter, 1948-circa 1963 (Box 1)
- Reiss-Davis Clinic for Child Guidance, Los Angeles, Calif., 1960-1961 (Box 1)
- Reports, 1936-1948, undated (Box 2)
- Speeches and lectures (Box 2)
  - Axelrode, Jeanette (Box 2)
  - Deri, Susan K., 1960, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Domarus, Eilhard von, notes from a discussion by Knoepfmacher (Box 2)
  - Eads, Laura K., 1948 (Box 2)
  - Freud, Anna, 1929, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Martin, Alexander Reid (Box 2)
  - Ophuijsen, Johann H. W. van (Box 2)
  - Reiss-Davis Clinic, Psychotherapy in a Child Guidance Clinic, Los Angeles, Calif., lectures, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Stuyvesant Polyclinic, New York, N.Y., lecture notes, 1961 (Box 2)
- Writings (Box 2)
  - By Knoepfmacher (Box 2)
    - “August Aichhorn's Work... Case Work Therapy” (Box 2)
    - Class papers, 1940-1941, undated (Box 2)
    - “A Conflict Episode Analysis” (Box 2)
    - “The Family Equilibrium and Its Significance for Child Therapy” See also Closed (Box 2)
    - “Family Interrelationships as They Affect Psychotherapy” (Box 2)
    - “The Latent Depression in the Preschool Child,” with Hyman Spotnitz (Box 2)
    - “The Need for Reality Testing in Borderline Cases” (Box 2)
    - “The Use of Play in Treatment in a Child Guidance Clinic” See also Closed, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Untitled, with Betty Filer (Box 3)
    - Printed matter (Box 3)
  - By others (Box 3)
    - Ayres, Dr. [?], “Instincts and Their Vicissitudes” (Box 3)
    - Bauer, John, “Similarities and Differences... of Monozygotic Twins” (Box 3)
    - Erikson, Erik H., “The Roots of Virtue” (Box 3)
    - Ekstein, Rudolf, three articles (Box 3)
    - Goldman, Harriet, “Word by Word” (Box 4)
    - Levin, Beatrice, “Living with Reality” (Box 4)
    - Love, Sidney, and Yonata Feldman, “The Disguised Cry for Help” (Box 4)
    - Merwin, P., “Ego Ideal” (Box 4)
    - Rapoport, Lydia, “Creativity in Social Work” (Box 4)
    - Shasof, Myron R., “Becoming a Psychoanalyst (1918-1920)” (Box 4)
    - Stern, George, class paper, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Tauber, Gisella, “Crisis of Leadership in Society and Therapy” (Box 4)
    - Unidentified (Box 4)
      - Titled (Box 4)
      - Untitled (Box 4)
    - Various authors (Box 4)
      - “The Family as a Communication System” (Box 4)
      - Printed matter (Box 4)
- Closed material (Box X5)
  - Cases (Container 1) (Box X5)
    - A-F, (8 folders) (Box X5)
    - F-W, (9 folders) (Box X6)
  - Group therapy, 1949 (Container 1) (Box X6)
  - Jewish Board of Guardians, Time and Treatment Project, 1949-1950 (Container 1) (Box X6)
  - Letters to Knoepfmacher, 1960 (Container 1) (Box X6)
  - Writings (Box X6)
    - By Knoepfmacher (Box X6)
      - “The Family Equilibrium and Its Significance for Child Therapy” (Container 2) (Box X6)
      - “The Use of Play in Treatment in a Child Guidance Clinic” (Container 3) (Box X6)